Guide to the Steve Early Communications Workers of America Papers TAM.603
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Steve Early Communications Workers of America Papers
1987-2007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Early, Steve
TAM.603
6.25 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons and two folders.
Steve Early was an organizer, strike strategist, labor educator, and lawyer, and a national staff member of the Communications Workers of America. He is the author of Embedded With Organized Labor (2009) and his articles, reviews, and op-ed pieces have appeared in labor, progressive and mainstream periodicals and newspapers. This collection documents the struggles of the Communications Workers of America in New York, New Jersey, and New England with the NYNEX telephone company, SNET, SBC, and Verizon, and includes contract campaigns, strike, and organizing materials from the 1980s until 2007. Materials included in this collection are meeting notes, memos, newsletters, circulars, fliers, clippings, injunction-related legal materials, and several posters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Steve Early in 2011. The accession number associated with this gift is 2011.139.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into four series:
Series I: Communications Workers of America Organizing Materials
Series II: NYNEX Strike
Series III: Southern New England Telephone (SNET)/SBC Communications Strikes
Series IV: Verizon Strike and Contract Campaigns
Historical/Biographical Note
Steve Early was an organizer, strike strategist, labor educator, lawyer, and a national staff member of the Communications Workers of America (CWA). CWA-represented telephone workers in the Northeast participated in national, regional or statewide strikes in 1983, 1986, 1989, 1998, 2000, 2004, and 2011. During these struggles the CWA cooperated with the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, which also represented some telecommunications workers. As many as 60,000 workers in New York and New England were involved in the anti-concession strikes during this period at NYNEX and other major telecommunications employers. The four month NYNEX strike in 1989 defeated health care cost shifting. The CWA also struggled against employers' give-back demands, including the demand for forced overtime, and struggled to defended defined benefit pensions and retiree health coverage. The CWA also fought for card check unionization, and for employer neutrality during organizing campaigns, especially at Verizon Wireless, the company's fast-growing and almost entirely non-union cellular subsidiary.
As a CWA representative in this region and telecommunications industry strike coordinator, Early was involved in local contract negotiations, helping to publicize strike issues, organize mass rallies and marches, pressure company and public officials for favorable settlements, and generate grassroots community-labor support. Early is also the author of Embedded With Organized Labor (2009) and his articles, reviews, and op-ed pieces have appeared in labor, progressive and mainstream periodicals and newspapers.
Related Archival Materials
His blog was archived by the Tamiment Library. A link can be found here: http://webarchives.cdlib.org/site/sw1h708z0m
Scope and Contents
This collection contains files collected, and in some instances created by Steve Early in his roles as a Communications Workers of America (CWA) official and as a writer on labor topics. The collection documents the struggles of the CWA in New York, New Jersey, and New England with the NYNEX telephone company and other major telecommunications employers, such as Verizon and the Southern New England Telephone Company, including contract negotiations and strikes. These materials are from New York and New England CWA locals and CWA District 1, from the 1980s until 2007. Among the materials are meeting agendas and notes, internal union memos, strike strategy memos and training materials, injunction-related legal papers, daily newsletters on strike proceedings, flyers, clippings, circulars and other printed ephemera, and several oversized posters. The collection also documents Early's work as an organizer for the CWA and success in campaigning and collaborating with other unions and social justice groups to achieve change in the union.
Separated Materials
A run of the Communication Workers of America District 1 Hot Line was separated for library cataloging. A copy of Billionaires for Bush: How to Rule the World for Fun and Profit was also separated to the library.
Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- Telephone companies -- New England.; Telecommunication |x Employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State); Strikes and lockouts -- Telephone companies -- New York (State); Telecommunication |x Employees |x Labor unions |z New England.; NYNEX Corporation; Communications Workers of America; Verizon; Communications Workers of America. District 1; Southern New England Telephone Company; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; Early, Steve; SBC Communications
- Series I: Communications Workers of America Organizing Materials, 1980-2000
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains materials related to Early's work in organizing CWA locals in New Jersey, New York, and New England, from 1980-2000. The members in these unions worked for the state, Western Electric, AT&T, NYEX, Cellular One, and other telecommunication companies. The collection contains organizing materials and literature, flyers, newsletters, Early's writings and email correspondence, and other ephemera.
  - Business Office Originals, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Cellular One, Dues Deduction Cards, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - "Cellular One Union News", 2005 (Box 1)
  - "Cellular One Union News" Local 1298 Newsletters, 2000 (Box 1)
  - "Conducting a Successful Strike" and Strike Strategy, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Communication Workers of America Materials, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Early, Steve, Writings on Communication Workers of America, NYNEX, and Other Labor Issues, circa 1990-2003 (Box 1)
  - Literature Files (Originals), Campaign in Residence, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Department of Public Utilities International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Clippings, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Picketing Cases, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Mobilization Reports, 1992, 2002 (Box 1)
  - New England Communications Workers of America Organizing Literature Samples, 1983-2000 (Box 1)
  - New England Communications Workers of America Literature Samples, 1983-2000 (Box 1)
  - New England Residence Office Campaign (Including November 1994 National Labor Relations Board Election Victory), 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - New Jersey State Workers Organizing Committee Anniversary Events, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - National Labor Relations Board and Business Offices, 1994, 1997 (Box 1)
  - OFS-Fitel Whistle Blowing Case, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Residence Contract and Office Closing campaign, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Strike Manual Materials, 2003, 2005 (Box 1)
- Series II: NYNEX Strike, 1989
  This series contains materials related to the strike against NYNEX (later Verizon) by 60,000 Communications Workers of America (CWA) and International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) strikers in the Northeast in October and November of 1989. The strike was about healthcare cuts at the company for the workers. The series contains mobilization reports, clippings, flyers, posters, memoranda, negotiations materials, newsletters, buttons, strike kits and other organizing materials, a cassette tape, and other materials generated by the strikers and the strike organizers.
  - "Boston Talks," Communications Workers of America Cassette Tape and Strike Button, undated (Box 1)
  - Communications Workers of America Mobilization Reports, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act (COBRA) Suit, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Flynn, Raymond, 1989-1998 (Box 1)
  - Flynn, Raymond, 1989, 1998 (Box 1)
  - "Internal Sabotage" Clipping, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Local 2222 Department of Labor Investigation, 1990 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Bulletins, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Bulletins, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Clippings, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Clippings, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Clippings, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Clippings, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Clippings, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Clippings and Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Health Benefits Materials, 1989 (Box 1)
  - NYNEX Strike Materials, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Materials, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Materials, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Materials, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Materials, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Negotiation Materials, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Postmortem, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Postmortem, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Postmortem, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Postmortem, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Postmortem, 1989 (Box 2)
  - NYNEX Strike Postmortem, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Paul O'Brien Rally, 1989
  - Press Chronology File, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Strike Kit, 1989 (Box 2)
- Series III: Southern New England Telephone (SNET)/SBC Communications Strikes, 1998-2004
  This series contains materials from two different strikes; the first was a strike against Southern New England Telephone (SNET) by the Communications Workers of America (CWA), Local 1298 and the Connecticut Union of Telephone Workers (CUTW) in Hamden, Connecticut. The strike lasted 28 days in August and September of 1998. The materials related to the strike include clippings, strike bulletins, bargaining and negotiations materials, campaign flyers, meeting agendas, strike strategy and training materials, final settlement documents, injunction-related legal papers, photographs (including photographs of Vice President Al Gore at the strike), correspondence, and other materials.
  The other strike in this series is related to a four day walkout that was planned by the CWA against SBC Communications in May 2004, due to a stall in negotiations. The materials include clippings, materials on a tentative contracts, healthcare materials, and some material with organizing with Jobs with Justice.
  - Bell Atlantic Strike, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Booklets, 1998, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Jobs with Justice (Box 2)
  - Jobs with Justice Clippings (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Bargaining and Mobilization, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike Clippings, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Connecticut Union of Telephone Workers and Communications Workers of America Local 1298 Packet, May 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Four Day Walkout and Tentative Contract, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Health Benefits, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Healthcare Day, Jobs with Justice, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Flyers, Clippings, and Mobilization Report, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Medicare "Reform" Clippings, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC Communications: Strike, Retirees, 2004 (Box 2)
  - SBC-SNET Strike Posters, undated (Box Shared Tamiment XOS001)
  - SNET: Agenda Book, 1998 (Box 2)
  - SNET: Bargaining Materials, Pre Strike Planning, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET: Bargaining Notes, Mediators, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET: Bargaining Website Printouts, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET: Carrier Switch Campaign, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET: Camp Operators Services, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET: Mediated Talks Bargaining Proposals, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Bulletins, Contract Highlights, and Tentative Agreement, Sep 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Bulletins, Flyers, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Clippings, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Clippings, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Clippings, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Clippings, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Clippings, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Clippings and Bargaining Materials, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Contract and Supplemental Agreement, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Handwritten Notes, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Hartford, Connecticut Rally, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Member Relief Fund, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Meridan, New Hampshire September 3 Rally, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Negotiations, Tentative Agreements, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: New Haven, Connecticut Rally, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Notepads, 1998 (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Photographs, undated (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Photographs, Al Gore at Rally, undated (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Photographs, Members and Kids, undated (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Photographs, Miglio, Daniel's House, undated (Box 3)
  - SNET Strike: Photographs, Mobile Picketing, undated (Box 4)
  - SNET Strike: Photographs, Pilot Pen, undated (Box 4)
  - SNET Strike: Post Strike Bulletins, undated (Box 4)
  - SNET Strike: Post Strike Press, 1998 (Box 4)
  - SNET Strike: Pre and Post Strike Materials, 1998 (Box 4)
  - SNET Strike: Sign-In Sheet, 1998 (Box 4)
  - US West Incorporated Strikes, 1998 (Box 4)
- Series IV: Verizon Strikes and Contract Campaigns, 1999-2007
  This series relates to the strike in 2000 and the later contract campaigns against Verizon (which had recently formed from a merger of Bell Atlantic and GTE) in the 2000s. In 2000, 85,000 CWA and IBEW workers on the East Coast (12 states) went on strike for three weeks in August 2000 over mandatory overtime. Other materials in the series are related to contract campaigns throughout the early 2000s against Verizon over different labor practice, layoffs, and cut benefits at local unions in the northeast. At different points, organizers like Early worked with other social justice organizations, like Jobs with Justice, to mobilize workers. The materials in this series include mobilization reports, flyers, clippings, email correspondence, posters, bargaining and negotiations materials, research reports, strike bulletins, organizing materials, and other ephemera.
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Bargaining Briefings and Post Strike Materials, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Clippings and Flyers, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Clippings, Bulletins, and Flyers (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Clippings, Bulletins, and Flyers (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Clippings (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Mobilization Files and Time Table, 1999-2001 (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Post Strike Clippings, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - 2000 Verizon Strike: Strike Buttons (Box 4)
  - April 4th Meeting with the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, undated (Box 4)
  - August 13th Healthcare Meeting, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Bell Atlantic Verizon Campaign Materials, Strikes, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Billionaires for Bush Materials, Allies, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Cambridge, Massachusetts Hearing, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Canisius Called: Letter Draft, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Carrier Switch, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Carrier Switch: Community Campaign Against Corporate Greed at Verizon, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Circuit City, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Communications Workers of America Agreement with Verizon New England, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Communications Workers of America Defense Fund and Members Relief Fund, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Communications Workers of America Local 1122, Buffalo, New York, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Communications Workers of America Local 1122, Buffalo, New York, 2004-2005 (Box 4)
  - "Conducting a Successful Strike" Packet, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Cost Sharing Correspondence, 2003 (Box 4)
  - December Store Actions, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Early, Steve Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 5)
  - Flyers, undated
  - "Fighting for Our Future at Verizon" Instructors Guide, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Frontline Forum, 2003 (Box 5)
  - "Future of Verizon" Op-Ed, 2003
  - Gay Semel Legal Memo, 2004 (Box 5)
  - General Mobilization Plan, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Greater Southeastern Mass Labor Council CDs, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Greenwich, Connecticut Demonstration Flyer, Jul 12, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Handwritten Notes, 2003 Verizon Contract Campaign (Box 5)
  - Healthcare Issues, 2003 (Box 5)
  - International Brotherhood of Electric Workers-Communications Workers of America Solidarity Appeal Clippings, 2003 (Box 5)
  - International Brotherhood of Electric Workers Verizon Wireless, Feb 2005 (Box 5)
  - Jobs with Justice, Allies, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Jobs with Justice Meeting, Jul 29, 2003 (Box 5)
  - July 25 Board of Directors Action, 2003 (Box 5)
  - July 31 Rally, 2003 (Box 5)
  - June Verizon Rally, Jun 2004 (Box 5)
  - Kara Dewitt Firing, Jun 2005 (Box 5)
  - Labor Community Support, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Labor Day Events, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Lay Off Decisions, Court Proceedings, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Local 1400, Deborah Yandow Grievance, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Local 1400, Lists, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Local 1400, Strike Preparation, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Mannheim and Communications Workers of america Response Article, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Massachusetts Senator Requests, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Mobilization Coordinators Lists, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Mobilization Literature, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Mobilization Reports, 2000-2003 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina Strike Solidarity, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Organizing Slides, undated (Box 5)
  - Political Outreach, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings and List, 2000, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Radio Shack Action, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Redlining Campaign, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Regional Verizon Bargaining Reports, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Retirees, Allies, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Scholars, Artists, and Writers for Social Justice (SAWSJ)/Jobs with Justice-United Students Against Sweatshops (USAS) Support, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Strike Authorization Materials, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Strike Fundraising, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Strike Op-Eds, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Strike Rally, 2005 (Box 5)
  - "Tear Down the Wall at Verizon" Packet, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Upstate New York Stop the Verizon Sale, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Ads, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Bargaining Council, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Bargaining Council Agenda, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Bargaining Council Powerpoint Presentation, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Campaigns, 2003-2007 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Clippings, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Consumer Outreach, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Bargaining Materials, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Clippings, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Correspondence, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Correspondence and Flyers, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Healthcare Cuts Flyers, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Healthcare Stickers and Clippings, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Mobilization, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Mobilization, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Mobilization, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Mobilization and Negotiations, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Press Coverage, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Contract Campaign: Unity at Verizon Materials, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon, Consumer Issues, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Meeting with International Brotherhood of Electric Workers, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Mergers, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Mobilization Materials, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Organizing Materials, Jun 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Prepaid Phonecards, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Service Quality Clippings, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Service Quality Plant Tours, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Strike Posters, undated (Box Shared Tamiment XOS001)
  - Verizon Strike Preparation Plan Documents, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Strike Strategy, 2000, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Talking Points, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Target Area Clipping, 2004 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Bargaining, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Campaign Materials including Agreement between Verizon and the Communications Workers of America for 2002-2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Fact Sheet, undated (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Fightback Plan, 2004-2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Organizing Literature, 2001, 2004-2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Protests, Dec 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Solidarity Campaign with Jobs with Justice, Jul 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Solidarity Campaign with Jobs with Justice and Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Stores, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Store "Shameless Campaign", 2003 (Box 6)
  - Verizon Wireless Training, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Vermont Governor Dean Event, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Wallingford, Connecticut Campaign, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Wyeth Board of Directors, 2003 (Box 6)